<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached upon the fifth of November, 1678 at St. Clements Danes / by Gregory Hascard.</title>
            <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25415</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08951624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08951624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1286:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached upon the fifth of November, 1678 at St. Clements Danes / by Gregory Hascard.</title>
                  <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. and B.G. for William Crook,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42077:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Upon the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1678. AT St. CLEMENTS <hi>Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By GREGORY HASCARD, D. D. Rector of the ſaid Church and one of his Majeſties Chaplains in ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Jan. 22.1678.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>Guil. Jane.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S.</hi> and <hi>B. G.</hi> for <hi>William Crook</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42077:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable JOHN Earl of <hi>Exeter,</hi> my Noble Lord and Patron.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am very ſenſible how much unworthy this following Diſcourſe is of your Lordſhips judgement, which nature made quick and ſolid; and Books and ſtudies have advanc'd: yet however, being earnestly importun'd, by ſome Friends of conſiderable Rank and Quality, to expoſe it to common view, and thinking this might be a fit opportunity publickly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that mighty favour, which your Lordſhip was pleaſed ſo generouſly to give, I have ventur'd to inſcribe it to your Lordſhips name, chooſing rather to undergo many cenſures upon it than miſs one occaſion to evidence to the world how
<pb facs="tcp:42077:3"/>much I ſtand oblig'd to your Lordſhips goodneſs, for what I there enjoy, where this was preach'd, I own to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Tule and undoubted Patronage, and my obligation ſwells the higher, being involv'd in that common debt, which the whole Nation owes to your Lordſhips Family, one of which was ſo happy an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in diſcovering this bloody Plot, and twould be hard for your Great and Noble Family to bear the brand, that ſome bot headed Romaniſts have ſet, calling this Plot only <hi>Cecils</hi> contrivance, and for thoſe that reap'd the benefit not to acknowledge the loyalty and good ſervice of a <hi>Cecil</hi> done to Church and State, and therefore upon theſe and many more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts with all gratitude and honour I ſhall ever indeavonr to expreſs my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble and moſt obliged Servant. GREGORY HASCARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42077:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED Upon the Fifth of <hi>November.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 124. Ver. 7.</bibl>
               <q>The Snare is broken and we are eſcaped.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHether this Pſalm is only Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical, and reſpects the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Calamities of the Jewiſh Church, and her Deliverances by Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as the Babyloniſh Captivity, and the Perſecution of <hi>Antiochus:</hi> Or whether it is only Gratulatory and expreſſive, of the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and eſcape from the intended Bondage and Miſery threatned by the <hi>Philiſtin</hi> and <hi>Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean</hi> Armies, and other neighbouring Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which often made their invaſions into the Jewiſh Kingdome: Or whether the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Pſalmiſt ſings in his publick or private Captivity, for Mercies conferred upon his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42077:4"/>ſingle ſelf, or elſe his People, or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or whether it be a mixed Song, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Writ frequently carrying a double force and ſence; looking back upon things or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours paſt and gone, and forwards, as Types and Preſidents, to prefigurate things to come. I find the Learned divided among themſelves, and 'tis not very material to determine, who hath the exacteſt truth on his ſide: It ſerving the Intereſt of the Chriſtian Church, that it is a lively deſcription of a rageing Enemy under the ſhape and figure of a ravenous and devouring Beaſt. <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. His number, force, and violence is pointed out under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of a torrent, deluge, or inundation. <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. The danger, ſubtlety contriv'd and laid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered as yet; and ſlyly carried on, ſet down, <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. in the former part. But the unſucceſſefulneſs and defeat of all theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching dangers and calamities, by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant and tender eye of Providence, in the later part, <hi>The Snare is broken, and we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things are conſiderable in theſe words.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The imminent danger and miſery the Church was in, by the plots and machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Wicked men,</item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42077:4"/>
               <item>2. Her miraculous and providential deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</item>
            </list>
            <p>What was then the condition of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, as tho it was a type or prediction, is now the State of a Chriſtian Church; the Danger and the Enemy, the Providence and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance very much alike in Features and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion: The truth and certainty of this bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Treaſon is ſo well known and confirmed, that none beſides a Romiſh Zealot, that hath pawn'd all his Faith upon the pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Chair, or which is as good, the dot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Legends of their Saints, can have the brow and confidence to call it in queſtion. This traiterous Deſign being evidenc'd from the judgement of Great and Impartial Men, who from an obſcure Light, a dark Letter to my Lord <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> made it as clear as the Noon Sun, to the ſatisfaction of King, Lords, and Commons, which cauſed the conſequent Acts of Parliament to call it an Helliſh Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not only of the Jeſuits, but Seminary Prieſts, from the Confeſſion of the Principal Actors, the Evidences product, at their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment, the acknowledgement of Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts themſelves; one whereof, the judicious and ſincere Hiſtorian <hi>Thuanus,</hi> hath wrote
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42077:5"/>the Hiſtory of it, that we may ſafely ſay, 'tis more fairly prov'd, than many Articles of faith in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 'tis the art and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that Church to keep their bloody Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of aſſaſſinating Kings, and murthering their heretical Subjects, ſecret and cloſe, till ſome fair opportunity calls them out for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick uſe, and condemns the deſign and attempt, if not proſperous; and diſavows it to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Vulgar, and the unſanctified ears of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, tho ſhe applauds it in conclaves and Cloyſters. But when<note n="⋆" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo 10.</hi> to Cardinal <hi>Bembo</hi> his secretary.</note> one of their infallible Biſhops called the Goſpel, that Fable of Chriſt, And <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> by them muſt be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have died Roman Catholicks; and that<note n="⋆" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux</hi>'s Praele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction deviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate Eccleſia.</note>
               <hi>Junius</hi> was cloven footed like an Ox, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence having ſet mark of Schiſm upon him: And<note n="⋆" place="margin">Sir <hi>Edw. Sands</hi> Spec. Europ.</note> that all Engliſh men, by the excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that they are under, had contracted <hi>Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Diabolicum,</hi> an helliſh Balckneſs, and have contriv'd ſuch fine Stories for the ſake of their Vulgar, and more ignorant Proſelytes; who muſt know no more than their wiſe Guides will give them leave: We may allow them to call this Conſpiracy a Puritan Plot, the State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft of <hi>Cecil,</hi> or what they pleaſe. 'Tis not our buſineſs now to prove there is ſuch a place as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42077:5"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> or the truth of this barbarous attempt, we ſhall only conſider it in ſuch circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as may advance the Providence and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and tune our praiſes and gratitude for it: the end of this days celebration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The cruelty of the deſigned Fact. Had the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Church been Heretical or Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, had ſhe ſwer'd from the Chriſtian Faith into the Mahometan, or renounc'd her baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Vows, and degenerated into the Pagan ſuperſtition or idolatry; is this the way to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the breach and difference? are theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per methods to confute Errors? is this the only wholeſome counſel and reaſon to renew our repentance, and make us Chriſtians once again? is to murther and kill, to convert? is to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in blood, to deſtroy our bodies, to bring our ſouls to Chriſt? Such ways for Converſion were utterly unknown, and never thought of by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and the firſt Planters of the Chriſtian Faith, and are highly unſuitable to, and unworthy of Chriſt and his Religion, which became victorious, and ſpread over the World, not by frauds or cruelty, but by miracles and argument, by patience, ſuſfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the innocency of its Teachers and Diſciples: And therefore its Author, <hi>Jeſus,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42077:6"/>tho ſolicited by his Diſciples, to call down, like <hi>Elias,</hi> fire from heaven (according to his mighty power) to deſtroy his fierceſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, the greateſt obſtacle to the propagation of his Religion, rebukes and corrects them, and tells them, <hi>They knew not of what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they were of,</hi> and that this temper was Ignorance and Fury, and not true Zeal and Faith; and therefore he would never in his greateſt ſtraits and miſeries, call down the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels from above to his guard and aſſiſtance, or like his Type <hi>Moſes,</hi> turn the Rivers into ſtreams of blood, but ſtill continued delivering his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Will, in ſafe and gentle methods, with prayers for, and compaſſion upon his Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, reſigning up his Soul into the hands of him that judgeth right: For the ſake of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity and the peace of Chriſtendom, all good men wiſh, that his pretended Succeſſor at <hi>Rome</hi> was heir to, and poſſeſt this gentle and eaſie temper, as well as aimed at his power and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. But alas! to the ſcandal of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, if we ſearch into the Records of Time, and turn over the Hiſtory of all Ages, and read the barbarous uſages of the Pagan World, we can either equal or over act them in the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries and Maſſacres of the Romiſh Church,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42077:6"/>that pretended mild and holy Mother: ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous are the files of Martyrs, that have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under their bloody hands, that we can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckon them by as large numbers as St. <hi>John</hi> doth his Catalogue of ſealed Saints,<note place="margin">Rev. <hi>7.5.</hi>
               </note> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> twelve houſand. For ſo the Hiſtorians tell us, that in the French Maſſacre in the ſpace of three Moneths, an hundred thouſand were ſlain, by the inſtigation of the tender Vicar of Chriſt, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More</hi> in his Divine Dialogues out of <hi>Vige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Peyonius.</hi>
               </note> and the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France.</hi> Murthered of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes</hi> ten hundred thouſand. Killed in the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi>'s perſecution thirty ſix thouſand: and in the holy Inquiſition in the ſpace of thirty years, an hundred and fifty thouſand, and what ſhould I tell you of the times of Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> and our own <hi>Marian</hi> dayes; of the Spaniſh cruelty to the poor Americans, or the bloody perſecution in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein an hundred thouſand Proteſtants were murthered by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh hands. What Kingdom or People have not felt their ſlaughtering principles, either by open violence, or ſecret poyſoning, or ſtabing? and this dayes brave attempt ſurpaſſes all the great exploits of all their bloody Predeceſſors: and every where ſo many have been, and are their cruelties, that that good Author, Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42077:7"/>obſerves, that Papal perſecutions do equalize or exceed the ten famous perſecutions of the Pagan Emperours: Here's the litteral Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and out writes the Copy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe <hi>Peter</hi> kill and eat; and when they have ſpoke the Prologue by the murther of a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſon in order to as deep a Tragedy as this, our indignation muſt aſſign the Roman Biſhops another Predeceſſor, his great Sire <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Fraterno primi madue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne muri.</note> who laid the Walls of <hi>Rome</hi> in his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood; as tho <hi>Rome</hi> Pagans cruelties were all entailed, and ran in the blood of <hi>Rome</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and are now become ſo natural to her, being eſtabliſht by her Canons and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we muſt ſooner expect an inſtrument out of a Cutlers Shop, than arguments out of a Jeſuits Colledge for our converſion, giving us no other effect of her power of Miracles, but that ſhe would this day have turned our Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers into blood; not remembring the wiſe mercy of that God, they ſay they adore, who when he reveng'd the ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi> in ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of fire and brimſtome, was careful leaſt the Righteous ſhould be ſwept away in the deluge: But here Prince and People, good and bad. <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of the Powder Plot. <hi>pag. 9.</hi>
               </note> Some Romaniſts and the Reformed, muſt all promiſcuouſly fall by one common blow,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42077:7"/>to be Pattern and Preſident hereafter of learn'd Cruelty, that they dar'd to act what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſear'd to think.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Policy by which this Conſpiracy was carried on, 'Twas called a ſnare in the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> time, and ſo it may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now: Naked Truth and Integrity are powerful and ſucceſsful by their native ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and internal vertue; his villiany and baſeneſs, which call for ſtratagems and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and live and thrive by political frauds. When <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf was to be baptiſed into Chriſtianity, only the reaſon and Miracles of her great Apoſtles, their plainneſs and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, their conſtancy and reſolution under perſecution made the way, and caus'd the mighty Change and Converſion; but when ſhe her ſelf is to reclaim onely the errors of a diſſenting Siſter, Conclaves and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, the State-craft of all their Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Orders, the ſubtlety of all their Emiſſaries muſt combine together to carry on this black deſign: How ſtrangely is Primitive Chriſtianity among them that pretend to be its greateſt Champions and Admirers, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from its firſt ſimplicity and open inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency into fraud and violence, inquiſitions and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42077:8"/>diſguiſes; cunning and artifice is their faith and piety, and the Court and Ceremony their Church, and their Biſhop inſtead of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Paſtor merits better the title of Stateholder; their Diſcipline and Cannons, their Articles of faith and Rules of manners, are coyn'd and fram'd to ſerve their power and Intereſt; and Myſteries of Chriſtianity are chang'd and become only ſecrets of the Papal Empire; the deſign of their counſels and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not to better and amend the lives of men, but to ſway and govern Chriſtendome. Good old Laws are relaxt, and new ones, call'd fundamental, caſt, to raiſe a portion for a Neece, or to enrich a Cardinal Patron, and their Exchecquer brought into the Temple, and call'd the holy of holies; that, what their Predeceſſors got by fraud, they might ſtill keep by the ſame method; the dreames and viſions, the extaſies and raptures, the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and revelations, and other pious frauds, us'd and countenanc'd by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (who calls her ſelf the only ſpouſe of Chriſt) to drive on their ſecular intereſt, makes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical world conclude, that Jeſus himſelf was only a great impoſter, and joyned with his Privy Council, the twelve Apoſtles, onely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42077:8"/>deſign'd to ſet up a new goverment, or only to lay us down ſome rules to trade by, and the chief factory ſhould be at <hi>Rome,</hi> a good School to teach men only policy and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and for an inſtance of their policy, which they call the Spirit of God, take the time for the election of Romes High-Prieſt, when they pretend the Spirit of God, is as famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly preſiding, and as fully operating, as upon the day of Pentecoſt, or baptiſme of the bleſſed Jeſus, yet ſo wide are their differences, ſo clamorous their factions, their buying of voices, their ſeting up ſtales, their tearing of ſcrutinies, their long diſagreement (as from the death of <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, two years and more) and other ſlie methods, that you may ſay of them, as an old Cardinal did, you muſt uncover the roofe of the houſe (ſo little room is left among them) for the holy Ghoſt to come upon them. And their famous Tridentine Council, was a better demonſtration of their cunning than their faith, and integerity, wherein they fancy the Spirit of God guided their pens, influenc'd their heads, and moved their hearts, he being <hi>totus in toto, &amp; inqualibet parte,</hi> and ſent every day (<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. of the Counc. of Trent. <hi>pag. 497.</hi>
               </note> as ſome then merrily ſaid) from <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42077:9"/>in a cloak-bag thither; yet beſide the lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their definitions and decrees, ſo many were their wily methods, and their labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous arts, that the Recorder of <hi>Florence,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> ſeem'd rather to keep the Chair than the Spirit of God, and little of good Saint <hi>Peter</hi> among them, beſide his Nets to draw ſome leſs diſcerning men into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of their Religion, and therefore more eminent was Divine Providence, that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered all theſe ſlie and ſubtle Serpents, that took them in their craſty wilyneſs, defeated their Counſels, and made them periſh by their own deſigns.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Loſs that would have follow'd had this deſign taken effect: Which is two-fold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of the Lives and Blood of ſo many.</item>
               <item>2. Of Religion.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Lives and Blood of ſo many. To ſecure the peace and quiet of this Nation, and to fix Religion ſafe from its undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the Great Aſſembly meets, a learned and wiſe King (the Prince alſo, by them in the beginning of their Plot, concluded to be preſent) Nobility and Commons with their large Train and Attendants, the Flower and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42077:9"/>ſtrength of the Nation, the Church and State engroſt, and enhous'd together, with their good deſign, ſtately buildings, and a Race of Kings ſleeping in their Tombs, muſt by theſe Conſpirators, be made an whole burnt Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and offer'd up to <hi>Rome</hi> ambition, and by one blow ſurpaſs, what ever Plague or Pamine, War or common Mortality, in many years could bring to paſs; and theſe would not have fallen alone, but Laws and Liberties, Charters and Priviledges would have died to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and have been buried in one common ruin: and all our peaceand freedome would have ended in Gibbets and Inquiſitions, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and heavy Burdens, and betrayed into a Papal Bondage: And this Land, that was never compleatly overcome by all the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and Armies of their Pagan Emperors in the ſpace of ſo many years, in a moments time, might have been conquered by <hi>Romes</hi> High Prieſt. <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of the Powder Plot out of <hi>Thuanus, pag. 5.</hi>
               </note> For ſo <hi>Catesby</hi> (as my Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian tells me) thought it not enough, that this, or that, or any ſingle Perſon, ſhould be aimed at, but that all together, and at the ſame time ſhould be comprehended in this Conſpiracy. For ſo he reaſoned with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, The King himſelf might many wayes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42077:10"/>be taken away, but this would be nothing as long as the Prince and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> were alive: Again, if they were remov'd, yet this would advantage nothing, ſo long as there remain'd a Parliament, ſo vigilant, ſo circumſpect to whatever might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen: Or if the Parliament, or the Chief Members of it, could be deſtroyed, there would remain ſtill the Peers of the Realm, ſo many prudent Perſons, ſo many pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Earls, addicted to that Party, whom they would hardly reſiſt, and who by their Authority, Wealth, and Dependants would be able, if occaſion ſhould be, to reſtore things to their former ſtate; therefore not by delayes but at one blow, all were to be ſwallowed up, and ſo laudable an atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to be brought to effect altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and at once. Thus did the Roman Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſtoop to her prey, and the whole Land was got within her pounces, but, thanks be to God, who hath not given us as a prey to their teeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Loſs of Religion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What might have been, had this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon been ſucceſsful. Had this Train of Powder and Deſigns been proſperous, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42077:10"/>a diſmall choice had been propoſed, to change you Religion, or to embrace a Stake, to violate your Faith and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for the Romiſh Creed, or elſe Lives and Liberties, Fortunes and all the Endowments of Life muſt be ſacrific'd; to Recant your Vows and ſacred Oaths, or elſe to expect a perpetual Priſon or a Flame, to ſuffer or comply, to have a Wrack either in Body or in Mind. Such hard propoſals ſhould have been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of your Peace, and a ſevere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it would have been to change the Religion of our Church, which we have Arguments and Reaſons ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm us, is pure, Primitive and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, into a Faith, that is but a Modern Contrivance and Innovation, begun by intereſt, made up of Fopperies and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and carried on by Fraud and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Such a Religion you muſt have had, which makes abſurdities, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Contradictions Articles of Faith, teaching you how by vertue of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, you may admire the glorified Body of your Saviour above, yet mangle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42077:11"/>it, adore, and devour it, at the ſame time here below, you ſhould have been taught to make your Prayers and Addreſſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in an unknown Tongue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the dead, that ſleep in the Tombs and Monuments of the Church, might have as good Devotion as the living in it, or if they underſtood any part of their Devotion, the work barely done, the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of their Lips and Fingers muſt ſatisfie for Zeal and intention of mind: you ſhould have been taught, that, though you die with a load of ſins, not thoroughly repented of and ſatisfy'd for, yet your kind Mother of <hi>Rome</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided an intermediate place between Hell and you, a ſecond venture from whence, by a Deputy Friend, a good Purſe, and a kind Prieſt, you may be diſcharged, and be Crown'd a Saint in that Church. You muſt be content onely to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in one kind, and be glad of the bread alone, for the dainty reaſon of the Lay mans beards, and the nice diſtinction of concomitance, yet point blank againſt your Saviours inſtitution.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42077:11"/>you muſt have been in that Church (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Thunder and Lightning upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to ſhew their indiſpenſible na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when the Ten Commandements were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd) will afford you Nine only; or at leaſt, uſe Art to conceal the Second, becauſe it Glares too much upon their Adoration of Images, and Invocation of Saints; and the Curious Diſtinctions of their Schools and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts have eluded the force of all the reſt. Such Prieſts, ſuch Temples, ſuch Devotions you muſt have had, ſo gay, ſo foppiſh, ſo full of Antick Poſtures, Scenes and Ceremonies, that you will find little difference between Old <hi>Rome's</hi> Theatres, and New <hi>Rome's</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Such a Religion is the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> which Magnifies Chriſt in Hymns and Songs, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and other lighter Services; yet Rivals him in his particular Power and Prerogative, in Adoring and Invoking Saints, ſom of which, while on Earth, were Vicious, and now we know not where they dwell; and others juſtly ſuſpected, if ever they were in Being. The jolly Sinner in that Church needs not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of his Salvation for want of Sincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, while Artificial Sighs and Cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Confeſsions, Pilgrimages and gentle Whipp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42077:12"/>Pardons and Indulgences ſo eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by privileg'd Altars, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Swords, Roſes, Hats, Church-yards, and other pretty Knacks and Devices; while a little Dole to the Poor, and more to the Prieſts, for a luſty Abſolution upon Attrition, and other faint Compoſitions with God, and Bribes for Divine Juſtice will ſerve the turn. Such a Church you ſhould have been in, who, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding her Pretences to Infallibility, can give her Members no ſufficient Aſſurance to judge by, whether they ſhall be ſaved or no; not only from their known way of Arguing, call'd Circle, proving the Scriptures from their Church, and their Church again from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, but from the Doctrine of Intention <note n="a" place="margin">Dianae Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </note>, (which is an Article of Faith at <hi>Rome</hi>) that if the Prieſt do not really Intend to do, what he outwardly pretends to do, all his Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance is Ineffectual; and this perverſe Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prieſt is not to be ſupply'd by God himſelf, <note n="b" place="margin">Ibid.</note> ſaith one of their Caſuiſts, and that the Prieſt may be ſo perverſe as not to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. <note n="c" place="margin">Eſcobar Tract. <hi>7.</hi> Examin. <hi>6.</hi> Num. <hi>41. p. 867.</hi>
               </note> Another of their Doctors doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſtates the Caſe where it may be allow'd; ſo that though you be Baptized, Communicated, and Abſolved, (things ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42077:12"/>neceſſary to Salvation by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,) yet you cannot certainly judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhall be ſav'd, except you have the privilege of God, and know the Heart and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of your Prieſt. Such a Religion you muſt have profeſs'd, whoſe chiefeſt Doctors and Guides of Conſcience teach men to break all the Ties and Ligaments of Humane Society and Converſation, telling their Diſciples that Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks; direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them how to Lye Artificially, to Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and Forſwear, to Cheat in Bargaining, to baffle Contracts, to exempt their Prieſts, though Guilty of Treaſon, from the Secular Judge; and before an Eccleſiaſtical one 'tis very difficult to Convict them, their <note n="a" place="margin">For a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>72.</hi> for a Biſhop <hi>64.</hi> See <hi>Diana Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> p. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes muſt be ſo many. Theſe Guides teach Subjects to Rebell and Murther, Children to be Diſobedient, Servants Unfaithful; by which, and many other lewder Doctrines, Skin'd over by nice Diſtinctions, by which they inſtruct their Proſelytes only more Learnedly to ſin; they would make the World only a greater Robery, and reduce it to its Ancient <note n="b" place="margin">For theſe and much more of the ſame nature, ſee the Caſuiſtical Writers of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez, Azorius, Leſſius,</hi> &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Chaos.</hi> In ſhort, ſuch a Religion the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> would have fore'd you into, whoſe Faith is Falſe and Erroneous; the Rules of Manners
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42077:13"/>laid down by many of her Penitentiaries and great Doctors perſwading and countenancing Vice and Debauchery; her Devotions Childiſh and gay, and propagated by Fraud and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Taking therefore this ſhort view of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Way, and being fully perſwaded that we are Baptized into this Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Faith is Primitive, Pure, and Apoſtolical, her Rules for Manners only leading to Virtue and Goodneſs, her Diſcipline wholſome and proper, and her Devotions decent and Manly; let us ſtick faſt unto her, <note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> and take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Advice, <hi>My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King, but meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What Religion hath loſt, though the Deſign was Unſucceſſful, yet the Attempt makes the Crime Scandalous and Horrid, and Deteſtable by all Mankind. Chriſtianity by the intended Blow lyes a Bleeding: <hi>Tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in Askelon.</hi> When the Uncircumciſed, the <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperours and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Princes ſhall hear of ſuch Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Attempts upon the Perſons of Princes, ſuch Bloody Villanies and Maſſacres upon their Subjects, and That by her that Arrays her ſelf with the fine Names of the only Catholick, Apoſtolical, Infallible, moſt Holy, and only
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42077:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtian Church; and Perjuries and Murders, Rebellion and Diſloyalty are defended by the Nice Doctrines of their Schools, will they not conclude in Diſdain: Here's the Principles of a Chriſtian, theſe Spring from their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, theſe are the Doctrines and Precepts of their Commander and Maſter, Jeſus? Are theſe the tame Lambs and Doves of Chriſtianity? Are theſe they that fear Damnation for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? Are theſe the gentle Martyrs for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Peace, for Conſcience and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Are theſe the meek Servants of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that calls himſelf the Servant of Servants? Chriſtians! Away with them to the Lyons and Fires again. Let us invade their Territories, ſet up our <hi>Alcoran</hi> for their <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and our <hi>Mahomet</hi> for their <hi>Chriſt,</hi> againſt whom we dare not Rebell, leſt we forfeit that Luxurious Paradiſe. The Bloody Doctrines and Rebellious Practices of the Infallible Chair hath ſtain'd more the Beauty of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſtop'd its progreſs and Victories over the Superſtitions and Idolatries of the Gentile World, and loſt more Proſelytes, than ever their buſie Emiſſaries, their <hi>Chriſtaviers</hi> and other zealous Planters have Converted and obtained. Will not an <hi>Indian</hi> Prince be afraid
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42077:14"/>of embracing the Chriſtian Religion, leſt he loſe his own Dominions, Life, and his Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Religion too, at the ſame time, which he now holds by a ſurer Tenure? Is it not a clear Argument and demonſtration to the <hi>Chineſian</hi> Emperour to renounce his Idolatry, and be Baptized Chriſtian, when he ſhall read how <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth and <hi>Frederick</hi> the Firſt (as one obſerves) fought threeſcore Battels more than <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> ſtirr'd up by the Peaceable Popes of <hi>Rome?</hi> Is it not a fair perſwaſion for all Princes to become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when they ſhall hear of the Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Excommunications, and that unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Power of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt, in diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Crowns and Sceptres, upon the pretence of Profuſeneſs or Breach of Faith, for Perjury or Magick, for Sacrilege or Hereſie, for Schiſm, or Violence to a Cardinal, and for many other Cauſes laid down by their flattering Caſuiſts, or for almoſt any thing, when his Holineſs is out of Humour? and they give us a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of <hi>Childerick,</hi> who was deprived from being King of <hi>France,</hi> becauſe he was a little eaſie natur'd, not given to Action, nor ſo wiſe as his Neighbours, whereby he was unfit for Rule; <note n="a" place="margin">Fowlis Hiſt, <hi>p. 113.</hi>
               </note> though <hi>Benedict</hi> the Ninth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42077:14"/>at Twelve years of Age was made Vicar of Chriſt, and his little Holineſs was as Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the beſt of them, and fitter for the Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of their Devotions than any. When they ſhall read of that Jolly Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> Excommunicating <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and publiſhing a <hi>Croiſada</hi> againſt her, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France;</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourteenth, Excommunicating and Damning <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, renewed by <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth; and the turbulent carriage of <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, in the Reign of King <hi>James;</hi> and thence (as a good Author notes) as it's natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, this Black Conſpiracy came; for ſeldom was the Thunder of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſcharged, but a Showre of Blood fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. When <hi>Adrian</hi> the Fourth ſhall chide <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa</hi> the Emperour, for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Stirrup wrong, and tread upon his Neck, adding Profaneneſs to his Inſolency, in applying the Prophecy belonging to Chriſt, <note n="a" place="margin">Pſalm. 9</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt go upon the Lion and Adder, the youg Lion and the Dragon ſhalt thou tread under thy feet:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Fowlis Hiſt. <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> When they ſhall read how <hi>Calliſtus</hi> the Second had <hi>William</hi> the Great Duke of <hi>Apulia</hi> as his Foot Boy, how <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime</hi> the Third put on, and kick'd off again
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42077:15"/>in Diſdain the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth his Crown: When the Pagan Princes ſhall read of King <hi>John</hi> reſigning his Crown upon his knees to <hi>Pandulphus</hi> the Pope's Legate, and of the Canonizing of <hi>Thomas a Becket,</hi> that Inſolent, Sawcy, and Rebellious Saint; and invoking of his Blood as meritorious: and the whipping his Prince and Maſter <hi>Henry</hi> the Second by the Monks of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> and that <hi>Champian</hi> and <hi>Garnet</hi> for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Treaſon ſhould juſtly forfeit their Lives here in <hi>England,</hi> and yet be reputed Martyrs, and have Glories about their Heads at <hi>Rome:</hi> that theſe can be the Methods to make Kings the Nurſing Fathers, and Queens the Nurſing Mothers of the Church? Will it not make them believe that Chriſtianity ſpread, and became Victorious, not by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Goodneſs, and Martyrdome, but by Falſhood and Invaſions, Murthers and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Armies? No Sect of Chriſtians have made True Religion more give ground, than thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs Chriſtianity, and all the World are <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> but themſelves. Their Adoration of Images are a Scandal and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence unto the <hi>Jew,</hi> whoſe Law is ſo rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42077:15"/>and ſtrait againſt them; and their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation is made up of ſo many Contradictions and Blaſphemies, that it made the <hi>Arabian</hi> Philoſopher <hi>Averroes</hi> ſay, <hi>Terrarum Orbem peragrando nullam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem Chriſtianâ deteriorem inveni, quae ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Deum quem tollit devorat;</hi> in all my travels I have found no ſort of Religion worſe than the Chriſtians, which Devoures that God it pretends to adore; and their many other ſoft and delicious Doctrines, have cauſed the Chriſtian World to degenerate into Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Vicious Lives; and to conclude Chriſtianity is nothing elſe but a Politick Maxim, to reduce Fools and Madmen and credulous Subjects into awe. Thus was this Church and State ſtruck at, but Chriſtianity felt the Blow; and while St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Suceſſor draws his Sword, pretending to defend his Saviour, and propagate his Religion, his Maſter receives the Wound, and he Crucifies the Lord of Life again, and puts Religion to an open ſhame.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the opportunity God took for this Deliverance. Juſt when the Snare, and theſe Conſpirators were ready; juſt when theſe proud Waves, our Enemies, in a violent Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent were all coming, and this horrid Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42077:16"/>was begotten, grown, and thriven in the teeming Womb, and ready to be brought forch; Divine Providence interpoſeth, ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it in its Birch, to the raine of its Parent. the Deity permits the Deſigns of Satan and his black Confederates to bloſſom and to grow, and through all the Intrigues and myſterious turnings of State and Policy, to arrive at their full maturity; then the Invincible Hand is ſtretched out, and crops them, to diſplay his Omnipotent Arm more, to make his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and his Wiſdome more ſought for and reverenc'd, and to be ſtronger Arguments for a grateful Mind. When the Trains and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Tyrants and malicious Men are ſo well contriv'd and laid, that their Paſsions begin to ſwell, and their hopes are brisk and ſmiling, and nothing but Victories and Praiſe, Triumphs and Succeſs do-rove with-within their Fancy, an unexpected Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſtops them in their full Cariere, blaſts their hopeful Spring, and all ends in a Dream. The Tyrant waxes pale, and mourns, curſes his Confederates, perhaps that <hi>Machiavel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that he and they are not Stronger than Omnipotence, and more Politick than the All-wiſe. When wicked Deſigns are in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42077:16"/>Egg, they may be cruſh'd and prevented by the ſlow and dull Methods of Humane Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, an eaſie hand; but when they hatch into a Serpent or Baſilisk, breathing out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Death, and Poyſon, and Deſpair, and Paleneſs ſits on every Brow, this Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger calls for an Infallible Eye, and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Arm for its Deliverer: Extremity, and the utmoſt minute of Cure, are the Seaſons for Divine Mercy: When <hi>Hezekiab's</hi> wound is become Incurable, when St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his Church begin to ſink; when <hi>Sennacherib's</hi> Regiments encompaſs and ſhut up <hi>Feruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> when Counſels and Armies fail, and the Secular Arm doth ſhrink, and nothing but a Wonder can prevent Deſpair; a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Eye looks down from above, Defeats the Enemy, and Crowns the Day with Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Succeſs. Thus did <hi>Englands</hi> Church and State both lye like <hi>Iſaak</hi> upon the pyle, the Flame and Conſpirators are ready for the Bloody Sacrifice; but an Angel thruſts his hand through the Cloud, a Bird of the Air tells the matter, and a Ram is caught by his Horns in the Thicket; the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators are their own Ruine, and now the cauſe of our Joy and Triumph, which leads
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42077:17"/>to the laſt, part, <hi>We are delivered:</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us theſe two Duties.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Faithful Remembrance of this Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly a future Dependance upon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Faithful Remembrance of this Mercy of God. This is all the return we can make for Divine Favours, paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately to reſent and commemorate them. But alas! Good deeds, though the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo cheap, do dye like Men, and are buried in the Grave of Oblivion, and have ſeldome a Reſurrection in the mind of the Receivers, thinking it meanneſs to make an acknowledgment that they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to God himſelf. He therefore well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw how ſoon his Miracles and Wonders in <hi>Aegypt</hi> would be forgotten, or attributed to Foreign Deities; He therefore commanded <hi>Aaron's</hi> Rod <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.10.</note> and <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 4.7.</note> the Pot of <hi>Manna</hi> to be laid up, and Stones to be erected at the paſsing of <hi>Jordan,</hi> to be conſtant and ſtanding Monitors to the deſcending Generations, of the Power and Bounty of God to their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers; and our Saviour had regard to the treacherous Memories of Mankind, when he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42077:17"/>commanded the frequent Commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Death and Paſsion, leſt that grand Attchievement ſhould ſlip out of the minds of men; ſo difficult it is for Sinners and Ungrateful men to record a Favour. The Pagans Adorn'd their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Spoils of their Battels and Victories, in Honour and Memory of the Aſsiſtant Deity: and the Sailers having eſcaped a ſhipwrack, hung up their <hi>Veſtes Votivas</hi> unto <hi>Neptune,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the favour of the Sea-god. We tell the long ſtories of our Sorrows to the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, we proclaim our griefs like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy, All you that paſs by, is there any ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row like to my ſorrow? or any grief like to my grief?</hi> We pen down the black dayes, write the Effects of a devouring Flame, or Peſtilence, Judgments upon Marble or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar with the Pen of a Diamond, we tell them to our Children, <hi>O paſſi graviora!</hi> and entail them upon Poſterity; but for Mercies and Favours, we cry not with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Come and ſee what God hath done for my Soul;</hi> we huſh them in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, we Degrade and Vilifie them, to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, our own Wiſdom and Power, and ſay
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42077:18"/>of them as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> of his <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Is not this great</hi> Babylon <hi>that I have built for my Honour and Renown?</hi> Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Affronts we write down in inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible characters, the Perſons, and Time, and all the aggravating Circumſtances are ever freſh and green.
<q xml:lang="lat">—manet altâ mente repoſtum Judicium Paridis—</q> and never laid aſide but upon a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental day, and taken up the next. Though our Memories for Benefirs at firſt may be freſh and brisk, yet the ſudden Flame of Joy at length changeth its ruddy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, grows pale, and endeth in Aſhes, and is blown away. And this day began to loſe its Solemnity, had it not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd by the New Traiterous Deſigns and Contrivances of the ſame ſort of bloody men. <note n="a" place="margin">Hiſt, of the Powder Plot. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </note> And if theſe bold Conſpirators, having found the Cellar for their Deſign, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under the Royal Throne, did ſeem to perſwade themſelves from that Accident, that God by a ſecret Conduct did favour the Attempt, we may now juſtly turn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42077:18"/>upon them, and in this ſtrange Deliverance acknowlege the hand of God; in a true Remebrance therefore of this great Deliverance, the Knife being taken from our Throat, the Flame quench'd the Snare broken, and the Tempeſt calm'd, and the Church and State, and every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon riding at an Anchor in a quiet Haven, let us acknowledge our mighty Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactour with our <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Our help is in the Name of the Lord who hath made Heaven and Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A Dependance upon future Providence. <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hitherto</hi> (ſaid the good man) <hi>hath the Lord helped us; he is god for ever, and changeth not, and his hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi> The Familiars of <hi>Rome,</hi> which haunt the Courts and Palaces of Princes, like the Devil in the Goſpel, ſometimes attempted to caſt us into the Water, by the <hi>Spaniſh Armado;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the Fire, by this Conſpiracy; and ſometimes by Civil Wars and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion (riding another ſort of Men) they rent and tore us till we foam'd again. <note place="margin">See the Book called the grand Deſign of Papiſts in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt.</hi>
               </note> But Providence that commands the Waves and Flames, kept us ſecure, diſpoſſeſ'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42077:19"/>the Fiend, and we are in our Wits again, and under our own Vines of Peace and Safety. And though the ejected Spirit thinks to return again, and make our laſt Condition worſe than our firſt; yet we doubt not (if our Prayers and juſt Zeal be not wanting) that Providence will put a ſtop to him, and ſay to him as he doth to theſe proud Waters, the ſwelling Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of the Ocean, <hi>So far ſhall ye go, and no farther;</hi> for think not that your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is enthron'd above only to hear the <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> of Saints, and enjoy his Triumphs, and liſtens not to the cries and groans of his Diſtreſſed Members here. He watches ſtill, diſcovers their Dangers, feels their Wounds, and ſends them Aids and Supplies, Power and Counſel to make them Succeſsul, that the gates of Hell and all its Auxiliaries might not prevail againſt them. Let the Times look Black and Stormy, let Predictions be never ſo ſad and gloomy, and we hear the ſound of may Waters, and the Fiend and all his Confederates ſit in full Conſult for the ruin of Religion, and nothing elſe is heard but the noiſe of Ravens and Eagles for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42077:19"/>the dying Corps, yet we can ſtand ſecure, an omnipotent Arm doth wield our Sword, and our Councel is All-wiſe, 'tis he that neither Heaven above, nor Hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, nor Earth and the Sea between, can skreen off his Divine and All-ſeeing Eye. The cloſeſt Dungeon and moſt ſecure Cell, neither Shade nor Night, as black as a Traytors Soul, can conceal their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy from him that Orders and permits, Diſpoſes and Prohibits for the Intereſt and Benefit of Religion, which tells us, <hi>That all things ſhall conſpire for their good who truly worſhip him;</hi> and that he that in former dayes did deliver us out of the paw of the Lion and the Bear, will deliver us from this Uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtin;</hi> and that we might not diſpond and ſuſpect his Promiſes, he doth further aſſure <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.35</note> us, <hi>that Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but my Word ſhall not paſs away:</hi> and therefore let us not ſink and deſpair, and cry out, <hi>Maſter, we periſh;</hi> but ſee the Train of Powder, and view the Snare, all lying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and Unactive, the whole Deſign of our Enemies Defeated; and with a grateful Mind ſing the triumphal Song
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42077:20"/>to God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.12.</note> with the Angels who ſtood aboue his. Throne and worſhipped, ſaying <hi>Amen, Bleſſing, and Glory, and Thanksgiving, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Powes, and Might, be unto our God, for ever and ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42077:21"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
